hello everyone thanks for joining it's
October 28 2022
active textbook group cohort 2
run the ninth
oh we're in the
every the weeks are shifted back by one
is that true
there's two 21s
or there's been some kind of other time
glitch
but today is 10 28.
anyways
um
we're discussing chapter four
continuing our discussion of chapter
four
so where would anyone like to
start with
does anyone have a general chapter four
remark or a particular question
that they want to look at
and that or anything else
uh Daniel it's brumlin
um there's just a lot in chapter four
obviously and it's sort of I think it
takes in a lot of
different aspects of active inference
and then sort of parse them all in there
and then throws out a whole lot of maths
so you know
it's unbelievably dense but
and and you know I don't know any math
so
but interestingly as I read it there's
some sort of themes that come out that
are sort of simplistic
and I'm wondering if somehow that can be
sort of
if you can sort of summarize that today
if that makes sense
um
they're just sort of like a
capsulated um
paragraph of the process it goes through
that was one thing the other thing was
um
the Box 4.1 the message passing and
inference so I didn't quite get the
difference between variational message
passing and the belief propagation
whether it can talk a bit about that
okay
yeah that's about it really
okay does anyone have any
thought on this in chat or or just
anything else to add
or we can
try to address these
okay
well one way to look at the theme
of chapter four or the kind of
looking beyond all of the technical
details
and the technical details it's kind of
like an iceberg because they could show
a little or they could show a ton
every time they show one they could also
show a whole
set of ways to get to it or not
so it's kind of like
um
uh maybe
it's like it's like a variable of the
text how much of the math they just
mentioned versus explicitly write out
because there's a lot of papers with no
equations at all like a philosophy paper
that will still say because of the
variation of re-energy or because the
generative model is this way
so kind of referencing the same topic
and so but different texts differ in how
much formalism they have
what is the role of the generative model
in active inference
what does anyone think about that
um
or in the textbook where is any quote
where they use where they say a
generative model is blank
or this is the role of generative model
we can look for some too or any other
thought someone has
at the end I'm mean I think it says that
they that they can vary
depending on on the inference problem
that's one thing about generative models
yeah another
way to that that variation point is
really important
the variation is sometimes described
with like fine tuning within a given
inference problem
which is sometimes framed as perception
in the most fast time scale and learning
and memory in a medium time scale
and then also
different implementations or different
like model structures can vary across
inference problems
hmm
there's also different ways to like
write and see the generative model
can anyone just like list or suggest
how are generative models shown or
represented
so is that the um the effect to graphs
in which section
figure 4.3
is it
4.2
so how
um yeah
one View
of the generative model
is like this figure 4.3
kind of
classic slash common representation
the base graph View
with the nodes being a random variable
and edges being relationships among
variables
and so like if if every variable were
connected to every variable
like every time Point were causal at
every time point
every hidden Factor influence every
hidden Factor you just have like a fully
connected
all by all
causal Association Matrix
so that's like the weakest World model
and then you can say well the the
present is like the only intermediating
Markov blanket between the future and
the past
or this is the you know perception is
the only intermediating Markov blanket
between observations and hidden States
if you are willing to take those
um structural assumptions and embody
them in the model the sparsity of the
model
under many different ways of calculating
the model
it will it just like always gets easier
you might be restricting yourself to a
very local neighborhood of models
but pretty much the more you can
constrain the edges and the
combinatorics
people cannot add other remarks on this
but you're always simpler models are
just
simply easier to fit
better I mean better optimization
is always achieved by making
quadratic or curved type assumptions
it's like a general optimization
principle to make things on a smoother
more incrementally updatable
related problem
foreign
they deal with time differently
they deal with everything differently
time slash
space Etc differently
I'm sorry can you hear me now yes Ali go
ahead
uh yeah uh I just wanted to mention this
paper a clear look through densities
which
uh clears up some of the uh
misunderstandings or misconceptions
around a generative model because more
often than not people think of
generative model as just
a structural representation of the uh of
the entire of the external world but in
active inference
the generative model is uh usually
represented in terms of its recognition
density so this recognition density is
something that enables us to
uh or let's put it this way it's an
approximate posterior probability
density that inverts generative mapping
from consequences to causes so it
enables us to uh recognize the hidden
States based on the observations and
inferring the causes of sensory outcomes
and not not just simply as a static
representation of the external world
um
great Point Ali
to like kind of unpack this
and and this is a great
um great entry point
um the The Tale of Two Cities is a book
about two cities
uh the tale of two densities is some
work with ramstead and others and
there's a
uh at least some
stream on it
and the two densities are like the two
directions which a Bayesian type model
can be used which is in its recognition
capacity
and in its generative capacity
so one point is the difference between a
sort of like descriptive statistical
approach
whether with p-values
or any other type of um statistics where
you're just taking observables only and
describing them statistically
or summarizing them
that the two densities
are those two bases of the Bayesian
model
which is about its capacity to generate
data from hidden States
and as Ali said to be inverted
or to be able to perform inference on
hidden States from
observables
and that is exactly
the
um distinction
of s and O
s r
unobserved unobserved hidden States
of the world
which in a causal graphical framework
there's different interpretations of
what it means
that causal
Force but it's it's the GM family that
one is embodying
and then the observations are up
so
blue
I'm sorry I just was going to add to
that if you're if you're dead Okay
um I just wanted to I always love
listening to that live stream and
Maxwell really stated it really nicely
like the differences between
um the recognition density and the
generative density uh it was how he
described it was like if you're stacking
up dominoes
um the this and then you're gonna knock
them over right like so the recognition
density is like the stack of dominoes
and then the generative density is like
the action occurring between The
Dominoes falling down like I I always
like that and it's locked into my mind
and really kind of helps me get a grip
on maybe the differences
okay
um Brock or
someone what have you added this quote
for
um just on page 64 this is like a
referencing equation 4.1 which is uh
right here it just says that um
that the generative model is
[Music]
um
the point that prior and likelihood are
sufficient to compute model evidence and
probability
so
I guess it's a slightly more formal
specific definition
and narrow because right after that it
talks about
um computational tractability of doing
that and
that seems like the best
starting point of
the generative model is blank in the
book that I was able to find
nice good
summary like
in the Frog
jumping example
prior and likelihood
left side
prior
beliefs on likelihood of the Hidden
state
on the probability of the Hidden state
before the observation
likelihood model
the larger
Matrix
it has a different dimensionality
than this one the prior
and it's the mapping of different things
then there's an observation
but in a sense none of these beliefs or
likelihoods models are observed
the observation o
which is like the experimental data
actually being collected
is here
and then everything else are like the
cognitive States or internal States
or States as modeled by the
modeler
and then there's some updating
and in chapter two that was being
described like in terms of
the surprise self-information
Bayesian surprise
but in the context of what Brock just
read prior in the likelihood comprise a
generative model
prior likelihood
the already composed a generative model
but it's like it's like a car that
hasn't been run
and then there's some that's when data
starts being able to update the model
so that's why many times uh we see
equations
like a Bayesian
equation
whether represented graphically
or with like
um in like a just a single line form
uh because to specify a Bayesian
statistical problem
is to have specified the generative
model
and vice versa Ali
uh and I think it's a general issue
regarding uh the whole active inference
literature because whenever we read a
paper an active inference we need to be
quite clear about uh what do the authors
mean by each concept because for
instance in this that paper from
2022 learning generative models for
active inference using tensor Networks
uh they have defined generative model uh
in its traditional statistical form and
not exactly uh it doesn't exactly maps
onto uh this somehow more uh
comprehensive or modified definition of
generative model in terms of recognition
density and so on so uh yeah
and it also extends to every other
concept we encounter in any other active
inference paper
foreign
purpose of just bringing back to chapter
two
and this example
is just to
um
situate everything that's happening with
the
theoretical like data free math of
active
and also the data oriented aspect of
which is
uh
to give a deflationary perspective a
specified Bayesian statistical model
and then data
that that model has
legibility around
of course you can
you know have it you know it could be
the wrong model for the situation
and so on but
this is like this is like the
statistical scenario
which is just prior
likelihood
data
and then this posterior can become that
one's prior
and that's just a
all right yeah can be modeled different
ways
in continuous time industry time
and again the whole point is just reduce
the uh
theoretical
novelty of active inference
because uh it's
more like
Bayesian statistical modeling
in this
mode
than many other things
and so a lot of the questions and it's
it's there there are great questions
that come up and have come up in
statistics before but kind of in a new
way here
like these are General statistical
questions they're statistical questions
involving action
building on some of the causal
statistical developments from Pearl
and others
who
brought in like just the concept of the
Markov boundary
in in that like 90s 80s and 90s and
Beyond period
um it's using those kinds of
statistical techniques
developed for Bayesian statistical
settings in the last
five to fifty years
in the setting of action
and Niche Dynamics
also
connecting
in some way that's not fully
characterized yet
with some
uh more physics like
formalizations
like the Bayesian mechanics
but that's not the first kind of
connection between
[Music]
statistical optimization
and
physics theories
which is kind of the whole idea of like
why you can kind of roll the ball to the
bottom of the hill physically and then
the statistical optimization works like
that too
so
degenerative model chapter to kind of
return to four and
the
first part of the
of bronwyn's earlier question I think is
this chapter is
describing many important aspects
and two fundamental
types of generative models
those dealing with active inference in a
discrete time formalization and a
continuous time formalization because
there's also other ways to do it
probably
it's just giving
technical details
on what those generative models are
because that is the entity description
that's the unit of perception cognition
action that's the empirical model as
used in the computer
to recognize data to generate data
so this is like kind of the core a core
idea
and sometimes it's dealt and like um
yeah sometimes it's just mentioned but
when it's mentioned that's why this is
the textbook
so that in some other velocity paper
they're they're not going to have this
but this is kind of
what is being discussed when those terms
are used in
qualitative settings or in conversation
with all these caveat of course that
everyone is using it differently
and then in terms of like
scientific
review and in uh evaluating like a
technology or some claim or something
if someone says the generative model
does this or it has this characteristic
these are like the specific aspects
that
would characterize that claim being true
sounds good very interesting
um discussion on
degenerative model
how about the Box
Ollie
well as far as I understand it the
difference between variational message
passing and belief propagation uh
basically comes to
um the difference
um in a holistic uh view of the
approximate inference computation and
the recursive or
step-by-step computation of it so in
variational message passing
case we actually have the already
actualized trajectory for messages and
we know all the uh conditional
properties of children uh with regard to
their parents uh and uh with those
informations we can compute the whole
approximate free energy of the whole
process but for belief propagation uh we
need to compute that recursively in each
step without
necessarily needing to have all the
information for all the probably
condition proper probabilities of
parents per
I'm sorry children with regard to
parents
beforehand so but another important
difference between them is that uh the
belief propagation uh
uh takes account for all the messages
that has happened up to the point of b
or the point that we're
momentarily dealing with that point so
because of that we
divide the whole process
with the probability of the B because we
don't want to include the b in the
process uh yet so that's basically
something similar to a kind of deductive
way of doing inference and the inductive
uh way of doing that
awesome thank you Ali that's very
insightful
let's look at 4.1 and see where we're
seeing some aspects of this well let's
pull out one more level Ali what would
you say what category
of things do variational message passing
and belief propagation
what is the category that even makes
these things comparable
uh well the similarities between at
least the structural similarity between
these two ways of computation is their
dependency on uh the ex the expectation
of the conditional problem probability
so uh in each case uh we're just
Computing the inference in terms of
their expectation
and as we see uh even the equations uh
look quite similar to each other so but
as they've pointed out uh in the bottom
of the Box uh this is a slightly
non-standard use of the expectation
operator so we need to be aware of this
point as well because uh well if if both
of those expectation operators were
exactly the same there wouldn't be any
uh difference any uh similarities
between those two kinds of
um inferences schemes
all right thanks a lot for that
okay if you notice one is these will be
fun to see the
descriptions
of
and uh just yeah like what what
these expectations are over
keep in mind the expectation here is
about the central tendency of a
statistical distribution
not a Time projection
so talking about
as Ali highlighted the expectations on
variables
that doesn't necessarily have to be
a Time series prediction
in fact
one of the most important uses is just
to calculate a rolling snapshot
in the context of Prior and likelihood
distributions as incoming data come in
so they're like parameter
bidding
modeling approaches
and is it fair to say that for a given
analytically expressed Bayesian equation
so formula
it's possible to
take the approach of of working with it
more along one branch or more along
another branch
is that the case Ali
or anyone else
papers tend to like take one approach or
another but there's also some papers to
probably compare them
but they are they're distinct
implementations
potentially with some
differences in
outcome that would be interesting to
explore but is it the case that they're
both possible to be used
for a given Bayesian equation if we
wanted to do the frog jumping out of the
hands
could there be a variational message
passing and a belief propagation
implementation
uh well I guess so if uh the the kind of
situation we're dealing with doesn't
necessarily uh restrict us to use
the the global over the global view
versus the local view of the inference
then I guess both of them can be applied
okay let's save this way
sorry just yeah
uh yeah the variation message passing is
uh kind of uh let's say omniscient like
view of the situation because we know
all the conditional probabilities of
each note but uh for the belief
propagation we're dealing with the
explore exploit dilemma
hmm
also their computational implementations
could be different
so a given language or package might
only enable one
and um
one other well
let's return in our in the last 20
minutes back to the detection if we go
there we go there
um but this also relates to the factor
graphs
and some
mathematical equivalencies
with
Factor graphs and Bayesian graphs
that is some of the work since like 2017
and a little bit before of DeVries and
power and friston
where
these algorithms can uh statistically
have good
computational implementations
or just
how good exactly
probably is an open question
but these but uh
there are
procedural rules for calculating
large graphs of this structure
which is why they represent recent
developments in
Bayesian computational statistics
it would be awesome to hear from someone
who's working with those kinds of
uh large scale
implementations but that is my kind of
outside interpretation
foreign
Ollie good
uh and also there are some recent
developments
um
in the uh for um I mean making these
kind of computations uh more tractable
and uh making uh the reducing the
complexity uh classes of the
computations
um one example is this recent uh
algorithm called branching time active
inference developed by theophy champion
and others and also
the work done by Baron millage such as
the inference learning or the
hybrid predictive coding is also
an attempt to reduce the complexity
classes of these kind of implementations
which can be
I I believe uh can be a promising path
towards uh achieving to a more tractable
and computationally effective way of
um Computing these inferences
nice thank you for that
yeah I
there's sort of like a meme like machine
learning is statistics and all that
so these
this chapter and
hopefully seeing how some of these
developments from
pure Bayesian statistics
but in the more recent era
there have also been
uh
computational
kind of interplay with
the pure theory development
for example
um
bootstrap based algorithms
non-parametric statistics where one like
resamples from distributions
and does that many many times
that kind of sampling based approach
was worked out
on paper
long before it became computationally
plausible
to actually sample
and store large amounts of information
and then once that uh computational
availability started to happen and
better sampling algorithms
and better Hardware
than
that area of Statistics can become
applied
which sometimes requires more
theoretical developments
but often not it's often just simply a
question of the implementation being
written
from like a code
or computational implementation
perspective
so there's a lot of equivalences in
active
but I think so the juxtaposition of
figure four three
generative models
with
Markov blankets first
and then saying these are different
heuristics computational implementations
model fitting approaches
and others others
that if you can state it like it looks
in figure 4.3
then this kind of
computational
statistical Branch will become
accessible
it's like if they showed here's the
linear regression
and here's the r method or here's the
python script
that you can use
or here's the um optimization here's
three ways that you can optimize a
linear regression
and there are multiple ways to do linear
regression
and there's different software packages
associated with them too
so it's like if your GMS have this
structure
then
these are
optimization
implementation approaches
that very importantly are not sampling
based
now
complexly enough sampling may have to
come into play in the real computational
implementation
but that's kind of a
deeper or more specific question to a
given
way that it's uh applied but just more
broadly these are not
just trying to sample data until the
landscape is like fully coded
these are
um models that with their sparcity
like what's not connected
embody
sometimes incredibly strong
structural assumptions about the world
which is why there's the whole question
of structured learning
because once you're structured in the GM
like we'll see in chapter six as well
the kind of structure is set and then
there's like a fine tuning where the
actual variables get tuned to the right
values
that's learning and perception
but also learning can be structural
um
so I hope that kind of provides some
concordances with the generative model
and speaks to its like
total centrality
inactive
in chapter four and connects it to
box four one
that's describing
some
exciting
techniques for computing large
base graph type generative models
one last comment on this and then we'll
still have more time just time for
kind of overviewing again is like
I think people have certainly said
before done anyone specific right now
but just that
there is a lot of focus on the Markov
blanket concept
and the sort of like
everything about the Marco blanket the
mystery
but less focus on the generative model
concept
so when people then thinking about
of how do we model organizations or
um
this cognitive feature
there's a lot of focus on like well what
are the nested Markov blankets
and now there's a way to
think about that as nested Markell
blankets
recognizing the generative model
that isn't just the entity scale
blanket
but that kind of nested Markov blanket
representation multi-skill systems kind
of like just general point
what gets often not brought up in those
situations is like
okay society's nested Mark all blankets
but what are the generative models
if you specify the generative model
you'll have also specified the markup
blankets
because you'll have defined the
particular things
embodied in the actual generative model
so it's like is it an active inference
claim
that a situation has been analyzed
in terms of interacting generative
models and generative processes
or is it a general Claim about
multi-scale systems being nested
so when we think about just the
encapsulating
matriuska nature
of the nested blankets
degenerative model is not
specified in more cases than not
hope that's an interesting and Fair
Point
okay
we have 10 to 12 minutes left is there
any other like
thought or question
Brock wrote Spooky inference in close
proximity to surprise generates noisy
definitions
I was just
kidding about ali uh saying lots of
different
names for things we call that spooky
action at a distance entanglement now
but at the time it was a bunch of
different things
when it was first
observed
and it was surprising
so anyways um
I don't know if uh yeah it's worth like
uh thinking
or just leaking like
lingering a little bit on the
intractability of
specifying like the model entirely in
most in a lot of cases
thanks yeah I think that kind of
um
anticipates some discussions that are in
like chapter six with a recipe for how
to make the generative model
and the difference between like
fully specifying
a quote toy model
which is to say like a model where you
can see it graphically
at like this like just kind of like this
like this is the whole model
um in that case you may be able to
create
a little information bubble where that
is the full model specification
but then in any real
situation
even like doing research
let alone doing anything with causal
feedback
in the loop
the the fully specified model just is
somewhere between doesn't exist
can't be specified won't be specified
shouldn't be specified
so then what what then
foreign
thoughts on four
or let's just look quickly to five
Ollie go for it
uh yeah just one small Point here uh I'm
not sure if
uh I mentioned it before or not but uh
there's uh kind of another type of
active inference of course we have a
very different classes or categories of
active inference but uh one specific
type is called uh sophisticated
inference which kind of deals with uh
the the situations in which
um well I mean uh instead of predicting
uh what would become later in at each
stage it tries to compute everything
that has come before or
in order to have a way to compute
um counter factual consequences or the
things that we need to
um or somehow the kind of uh
decision-making processes and so on and
um interestingly in the paper branching
time active inference uh they've stated
that uh this type of active inference is
a subset of branching time active
inference I mean if we just
put take that branching time active
inference and separate it into forward
and backward propagation uh trajectories
will come with a traditional active
inference and sophisticated active
inference so I think the main paper for
sophisticated active inference is this
one that I'm putting here so
yeah because that's just one small point
I wanted to mention
great point
thanks for sharing this generative model
knowledge
it's very
helpful
live stream 11 was sophisticated
affective inference
so that was
with a secondary or you know here
verbally secondary
adjective effective
reflecting that they were modeling an
affective variable or taking an
affective interpretation of their
model's cognitive function
they were doing affective inference
in the context of sophisticated
inference
which is as
um Ali described
allows for a kind of mapping and
modeling of past present and future
which is like why in four three there's
like a time minus one and time plus one
it could have been written as just time
time plus one time plus two
and been like a two-step planning
problem but also there's um
you can choose different pieces of the
time Horizons to model Ali
or a better way to a probably a better
way to put it is to say that in
situations where we have beliefs about
beliefs uh this kind of sophisticated
inference can come to play
instead of just bleeds about States
and
the composability of Bayesian graphs
is high
which is what allows all of these
different structural models to be
explored like nested models that
represent spatial enclosure nested
models that represent
counterfactuals
models that consider the past and are
able to reconsider the past observations
models that don't all of the like if of
memoryless process
wow
all right chapter five is quite
different and we'll just look through it
and see how different it is
it's gonna pick up on this message
passing
topic which will be cool to revisit
again and consider it primarily from the
context of neurobiology
in this chapter we focus on the process
theories that arise from chapter four
Central to this implementation of
Bayesian belief updating is the notion
of Bayesian message passing
microcircus and messages
cortical players
part of the mammalian brain mammal
neural Anatomy
mammal computational cerebral
neuroanatomy
abstract
hierarchical predictive coding model
motor reflex arc
in the spinal column of metal
policy selection
computational neuroanatomy in the mammal
brain
putative roles of neurotransmitters in
active inference
different neurotransmitters
and they're sort of like
putative
or
coarse grained or hypothesized
computational role
and different studies that support that
for that neurotransmitter
not saying it's like the only thing it
does or the only way to look at it just
they found empirical support for it
playing that statistical role in those
experiments
then
some early moves
towards integrating continuous and
discrete models
which returns later in the second half
of the book and the closing figure is
showing all of the three examples from
neuroanatomy together
planning
with those dopaminergic brain regions
then the prefrontal
cortical regions
on top
and the spinal
reflex motor behavioral art with action
so it's like when we've been talking
about planning as inference
and prediction and generalization
categorization as inference learning as
inference
action as inference
this is the graph
so it's a different chapter it's not as
equation driven
and uh
it's primarily based on those examples
of mammal
and generalized computational
neuroanatomy
so it's a cool
last chapter for the first half
all right
any other last comments
okay I'll stop recording thank you